const arr = [{"id":0,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following is not a characteristic feature of hemolytic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Increased neutrophil count","bool":false},{"option":"Reduced plasma haptoglobin level","bool":false},{"option":"Increased unconjugated bilirubin","bool":false},{"option":"Excess urinary urobilinogen","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased reticulocyte count","bool":true}]},{"id":1,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"A 2-year-old male child presented in emergency with sudden onset of jaundice and cola-colored urine since last night. He was put on antimalarial two days back for suspected malaria. On examination in addition to jaundice, he has anemia and splenomegaly without hepatomegaly or lymphadenopathy. His blood pressure is 80/50 mmHg, pulse rate 110/min, and no edema. What test will confirm \r\n a diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Hemoglobin electrophoresis","bool":false},{"option":"Urine D/R","bool":false},{"option":"Osmotic fragility test","bool":false},{"option":"G6PD levels in red blood cells","bool":true},{"option":"Liver function test","bool":false}]},{"id":2,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"A 25-year-old man is being transfused with whole blood. Suddenly, he develops a fever of 38.5Â°C associated with chills and flushing. Blood is oozing from the cannula site. What kind of transfusion reaction is it?","answers":[{"option":"Acute hemolytic transfusion reaction","bool":true},{"option":"Allergic reaction","bool":false},{"option":"Post transfusion purpura","bool":false},{"option":"Delayed hemolytic transfusion reaction","bool":false},{"option":"Febrile non-hemolytic transfusion reaction","bool":false}]},{"id":3,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"What is the definitive treatment for thalassemia major?","answers":[{"option":"Iron chelation therapy","bool":false},{"option":"Cryotherapy","bool":false},{"option":"Iron supplementation","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow transplantation","bool":true},{"option":"Blood transfusion","bool":false}]},{"id":4,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"What does corpus delicti mean?","answers":[{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Corpse that is pleasant to the taste","bool":false},{"option":"Body that is found at scene of crime","bool":false},{"option":"Proof that a crime has been committed","bool":true},{"option":"Proof of guilt of crime","bool":false}]},{"id":5,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the below-enlisted ranges best represent the mixed dentition period?","answers":[{"option":"7-12","bool":false},{"option":"6-10","bool":false},{"option":"6-12","bool":true},{"option":"6-14","bool":false},{"option":"7-10","bool":false}]},{"id":6,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following is true regarding Gustafson's method of age estimation?","answers":[{"option":"Provides the most accurate estimate of age","bool":false},{"option":"Makes use of incremental lines to estimate age","bool":false},{"option":"Consists of macroscopic examination of the tooth","bool":false},{"option":"Helps in age estimation between 25-60 years","bool":true},{"option":"Relies on the degree of calcification to estimate age","bool":false}]},{"id":7,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"What do red blood cells look like in hereditary spherocytosis?","answers":[{"option":"Bite cells","bool":false},{"option":"Macrocytic","bool":false},{"option":"Target cells","bool":false},{"option":"Microcytic","bool":false},{"option":"Normocytic","bool":true}]},{"id":8,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following is not a feature of polycythemia?","answers":[{"option":"Hypotension","bool":true},{"option":"Cyanosis","bool":false},{"option":"Pruritus","bool":false},{"option":"Hepatosplenomegaly","bool":false},{"option":"Headache","bool":false}]},{"id":9,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Mild hypochromic microcytic anemia is associated with which of the following pathologies?","answers":[{"option":"Hemoglobin H disease","bool":false},{"option":"Beta-thalassemia major","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12 deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Alpha-thalassemia minor","bool":true},{"option":"Diamond-Blackfan anemia","bool":false}]},{"id":10,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following is a cause of neutropenia?","answers":[{"option":"Addison's disease","bool":false},{"option":"Steroids","bool":false},{"option":"Allergic reaction","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":true},{"option":"None of them","bool":false}]},{"id":11,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"In which of the following conditions will eosinophilia be observed?","answers":[{"option":"Cushing's syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Autoimmune hemolytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Protozoal and parasitic infection","bool":true},{"option":"Chronic inflammation","bool":false},{"option":"Septic shock","bool":false}]},{"id":12,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following defines beta thalassemia?","answers":[{"option":"Reduced delta globin chain synthesis","bool":false},{"option":"Reduced zeta globin chain synthesis","bool":false},{"option":"Reduced alpha globin chain synthesis","bool":false},{"option":"Reduced gamma globin chain synthesis","bool":false},{"option":"Reduced beta globin chain synthesis","bool":true}]},{"id":13,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"How to check for Rh-sensitization in an Rh negative mother?","answers":[{"option":"Do amniocentesis","bool":false},{"option":"Do indirect Coombs test of the mother","bool":true},{"option":"Check antibody titers","bool":false},{"option":"Check blood group of father","bool":false},{"option":"Do direct Coomb's test of the mother","bool":false}]},{"id":14,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following occurs in leukoerythroblastosis?","answers":[{"option":"Presence of increased leukocytes in blood","bool":false},{"option":"Presence of increased red blood cells in blood","bool":false},{"option":"Presence of immature myeloid cells in blood","bool":true},{"option":"Presence of increased lymphocytes in blood","bool":false},{"option":"Presence of increased neutrophils in blood","bool":false}]},{"id":15,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"The majority of the type of Hemoglobin in alpha thalassemia with 4 allele deletions is:","answers":[{"option":"Beta-globin","bool":false},{"option":"Delta-globin","bool":false},{"option":"Gamma-globin","bool":true},{"option":"None of the above","bool":false},{"option":"Alpha-globin","bool":false}]},{"id":16,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Vaccination against which of the following microbial agents was added most recently to the Expanded Programme on Immunization (EPI) in Pakistan?","answers":[{"option":"Mumps","bool":false},{"option":"Diphtheria","bool":false},{"option":"Smallpox","bool":false},{"option":"Rotavirus","bool":true},{"option":"Human immunodeficiency virus","bool":false}]},{"id":17,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following factors promotes sickling?","answers":[{"option":"Alkalosis","bool":false},{"option":"Hypotonicity","bool":false},{"option":"Bacterial illness","bool":false},{"option":"Dehydration","bool":true},{"option":"Hyperoxia","bool":false}]},{"id":18,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"During the autopsy of a man, the coroner determines his age to be below sixty due to noting that a skull suture has not yet fused. Which of the following correctly identifies this particular skull suture?","answers":[{"option":"Delta","bool":false},{"option":"Squamous","bool":true},{"option":"Saggital","bool":false},{"option":"Coronal","bool":false},{"option":"Lambdoid","bool":false}]},{"id":19,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"What is not a feature of platelet disorders?","answers":[{"option":"Ecchymoses","bool":false},{"option":"Immediate bleeding","bool":false},{"option":"Hemarthrosis","bool":true},{"option":"Mucosal bleeding","bool":false},{"option":"Petechiae","bool":false}]},{"id":20,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following is not due to a functional disorder of the platelets?","answers":[{"option":"Glanzmann thrombasthenia","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet pool deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Gray platelet syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Bernard-Soulier syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura (TTP)","bool":true}]},{"id":21,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Where does the defect lie in sickle cell disease?","answers":[{"option":"Ankyrin","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobin structure","bool":true},{"option":"Protoporphyrin synthesis","bool":false},{"option":"Erythropoiesis","bool":false},{"option":"DNA","bool":false}]},{"id":22,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"A 4-year-old male child is being evaluated for a bleeding disorder. Family history reveals that his maternal uncle had a similar disorder, but his mother and father had no such problem. What is the mode of transmission of the bleeding disorder in this child?","answers":[{"option":"Autosomal dominant","bool":false},{"option":"Autosomal recessive","bool":false},{"option":"X-linked dominant","bool":false},{"option":"X-linked recessive","bool":true},{"option":"Co-dominant","bool":false}]},{"id":23,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"In which of the following conditions is streptokinase contraindicated?","answers":[{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"DIC","bool":true},{"option":"DVT","bool":false},{"option":"Acute MI","bool":false},{"option":"Pulmonary embolism","bool":false}]},{"id":24,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following describes the mode of transmission of hemophilia A?","answers":[{"option":"X- linked dominant","bool":false},{"option":"Autosomal recessive","bool":false},{"option":"Autosomal dominant","bool":false},{"option":"Mitochondrial disease","bool":false},{"option":"X-linked recessive","bool":true}]},{"id":25,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"What is the most common manifestation of von Willebrand disease?","answers":[{"option":"Joint bleeding","bool":false},{"option":"Cerebral haemorrhage","bool":false},{"option":"Rectal bleeding","bool":false},{"option":"Meningeal bleeding","bool":false},{"option":"Gum bleeding","bool":true}]},{"id":26,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following vaccines is given intradermally in the right deltoid?","answers":[{"option":"MMR","bool":false},{"option":"Polio","bool":false},{"option":"Pentavaccine","bool":false},{"option":"BCG","bool":true},{"option":"Rotavirus","bool":false}]},{"id":27,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following is the most common type of mutation seen in Î²+ thalassemia?","answers":[{"option":"Gene deletion","bool":false},{"option":"Translocation","bool":false},{"option":"Splicing mutation","bool":true},{"option":"Chain terminator mutation","bool":false},{"option":"Promoter region mutation","bool":false}]},{"id":28,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"The Bacille Calmette-Guerin vaccine is administered via which route?","answers":[{"option":"Intramuscular","bool":false},{"option":"Subcutaneous","bool":false},{"option":"Intravenous","bool":false},{"option":"Intradermal","bool":true},{"option":"Sublingual","bool":false}]},{"id":29,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"What is cheiloscopy used for?","answers":[{"option":"Identification of humans based on lip prints","bool":true},{"option":"Identification of humans based on hand prints","bool":false},{"option":"Identification of humans based on bite patterns","bool":false},{"option":"Identification of humans based on finger prints","bool":false},{"option":"Identification of humans based on foot prints","bool":false}]},{"id":30,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"When does the pisiform bone begin to ossify?","answers":[{"option":"Between 3 and 7 years","bool":false},{"option":"Between 10 and 12 years","bool":true},{"option":"Between 5 and 6 years","bool":false},{"option":"Between 1 and 2 years","bool":false},{"option":"Between 7.5 and 10 years","bool":false}]},{"id":31,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following is a feature seen in the whorl pattern of fingerprints?","answers":[{"option":"All of these are features","bool":true},{"option":"Central core","bool":false},{"option":"Two deltas which fall in the same straight plane","bool":false},{"option":"Intersecting ridges","bool":false},{"option":"More intricate than arch or loop pattern","bool":false}]},{"id":32,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"What is used to measure the stored form of iron?","answers":[{"option":"Serum ferritin","bool":true},{"option":"Serum iron","bool":false},{"option":"Serum transferrin","bool":false},{"option":"Serum albumin","bool":false},{"option":"Total iron binding capacity","bool":false}]},{"id":33,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"What is thrombocytopenia defined as?","answers":[{"option":"Low megakaryocyte count","bool":false},{"option":"High platelet count","bool":false},{"option":"Low leukocyte count","bool":false},{"option":"Low platelet count","bool":true},{"option":"Low neutrophil count","bool":false}]},{"id":34,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which medical condition is not associated with venous thrombosis?","answers":[{"option":"Heart attack","bool":false},{"option":"Guillain-Barre syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Inflammatory bowel disease","bool":false},{"option":"Nephritic syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Pneumonia","bool":false}]},{"id":35,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"What is the most common cause of vitamin B12 deficiency?","answers":[{"option":"Ileal resection","bool":false},{"option":"Pernicious anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Diphyllobothrium","bool":false},{"option":"Gastrointestinal TB","bool":false},{"option":"Veganism","bool":false}]},{"id":36,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which test is conducted to determine the cause of deficiency of vitamin B12?","answers":[{"option":"Serum methylmalonic acid level","bool":false},{"option":"Coombs test","bool":false},{"option":"Schilling test","bool":true},{"option":"Serum vitamin B12 levels","bool":false},{"option":"Serum homocysteine level","bool":false}]},{"id":37,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"When do thalassemia major symptoms begin to appear?","answers":[{"option":"Within the first 2 years of life","bool":true},{"option":"Within the first 3 years of life","bool":false},{"option":"Within the last trimester","bool":false},{"option":"Within the first 4 years of life","bool":false},{"option":"In Intrauterine life","bool":false}]},{"id":38,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following is the most common cause of chronic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Folic acid deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Hematopoietic growth factor deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency","bool":true},{"option":"Deficiency of trace elements","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12 deficiency","bool":false}]},{"id":39,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following cells will be found in a peripheral blood film consistent with vitamin B12 deficiency?","answers":[{"option":"Spherocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Schistocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Hypersegmented neutrophils","bool":true},{"option":"None of the above","bool":false},{"option":"Burr cells","bool":false}]},{"id":40,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"What of the following substances are found in mast cell granules?","answers":[{"option":"Bradykinin and mucus","bool":false},{"option":"Histamine and bradykinin","bool":false},{"option":"Histamine and heparin","bool":true},{"option":"Histamine and mucus","bool":false},{"option":"Heparin and mucus","bool":false}]},{"id":41,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Smudge cells are characteristic of which neoplastic condition?","answers":[{"option":"T-cell lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Diffuse large B-cell lymphoma (DLBCL)","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL)","bool":true},{"option":"Chronic myelogenous leukemia (CML)","bool":false},{"option":"Acute myeloid leukemia (AML)","bool":false}]},{"id":42,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following is the surest sign to determine that hanging was ante-mortem, rather than post-mortem?","answers":[{"option":"Hyperaemia of trachea and epiglottis","bool":true},{"option":"Fracture of hyoid bone","bool":false},{"option":"Ligature around the neck","bool":false},{"option":"Protruding tongue","bool":false},{"option":"Cyanosis of face and lips","bool":false}]},{"id":43,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"What is the most common cause of disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC) in hospitalized patients?","answers":[{"option":"Amniotic fluid embolism","bool":false},{"option":"Cardiogenic shock","bool":false},{"option":"Acute respiratory distress syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Sepsis","bool":true},{"option":"Trauma","bool":false}]},{"id":44,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following is not a cause of lymphocytosis?","answers":[{"option":"Lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Corticosteroids","bool":true},{"option":"Chronic lymphocytic leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Post-splenectomy state","bool":false},{"option":"Bordetella pertussis infection","bool":false}]},{"id":45,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"A 45-year-old man recently had a gastrectomy. He now presents with lethargy, weakness and parasthesia of the limbs. His MCV is 110 fL. What is the likely cause of his symptoms?","answers":[{"option":"Malabsorption","bool":false},{"option":"Somatic neuropathy","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12 deficiency","bool":true},{"option":"Iron deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Folic acid deficiency","bool":false}]},{"id":46,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"When is the second dose of the measles vaccine given?","answers":[{"option":"At 24 months","bool":false},{"option":"At 6 months","bool":false},{"option":"At birth","bool":false},{"option":"At 15 months","bool":true},{"option":"At 9 months","bool":false}]},{"id":47,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"A 22-year-old African American man went to the hospital to determine if he has sickle cell trait. Which one of the following laboratory tests can be used to detect the presence of hemoglobin S?","answers":[{"option":"Coombs test","bool":false},{"option":"Glucose tolerance test","bool":false},{"option":"Osmotic fragility test","bool":false},{"option":"Metabisulfite test","bool":true},{"option":"Schillings test","bool":false}]},{"id":48,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following results in sickle cell crisis?","answers":[{"option":"Vaso-occlusive crisis","bool":true},{"option":"Sickling","bool":false},{"option":"Autosplenectomy","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic crisis","bool":false},{"option":"Sequestration crisis","bool":false}]},{"id":49,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following is not classified as a platelet functional disorder?","answers":[{"option":"Bernard soulier syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombotic thrombocytopenia purpura","bool":true},{"option":"Glanzmann thrombasthemia","bool":false},{"option":"Grey platelet syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Von Willebrand disease","bool":false}]},{"id":50,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"How many vaccines are included in the expanded program on immunization (EPI)?","answers":[{"option":"7","bool":false},{"option":"15","bool":false},{"option":"3","bool":false},{"option":"10","bool":true},{"option":"9","bool":false}]},{"id":51,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"By what route is the measles vaccine given through?","answers":[{"option":"Intramuscular route","bool":false},{"option":"Oral route","bool":false},{"option":"Intadermal route","bool":false},{"option":"Intranasal route","bool":false},{"option":"Subcutaneous route","bool":true}]},{"id":52,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following is not an inhibitor of platelet aggregation?","answers":[{"option":"Dipyridamole","bool":false},{"option":"Acetaminophen","bool":true},{"option":"Abciximab","bool":false},{"option":"Aspirin","bool":false},{"option":"Clopidogrel","bool":false}]},{"id":53,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"What is the most common cause of macrocytic anaemia?","answers":[{"option":"Vitamin B12/B9 deficiency","bool":true},{"option":"Vitamin C deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Liver disease","bool":false},{"option":"von Willebrand disease","bool":false},{"option":"Hemolytic uremic syndrome","bool":false}]},{"id":54,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"What is the mode of action of corticosteroids?","answers":[{"option":"Inhibition of MCH-II","bool":false},{"option":"Inhibition of NF-ÎºB in leukocytes","bool":true},{"option":"Inhibition of the IL-2 receptor","bool":false},{"option":"Inhibition of nitric oxide","bool":false},{"option":"Activation of macrophages","bool":false}]},{"id":55,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following conditions is most likely to cause extravascular hemolysis?","answers":[{"option":"RBCs have less hemoglobin","bool":false},{"option":"RBCs have nucleur remnants","bool":false},{"option":"RBCs are less deformable","bool":true},{"option":"RBCs are more deformable","bool":false},{"option":"RBCs are spherical","bool":false}]},{"id":56,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following is not a subtype of classic Hodgkin lymphoma?","answers":[{"option":"Lymphocyte depleted","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphocyte rich","bool":false},{"option":"Follicular","bool":true},{"option":"Mixed cellularity","bool":false},{"option":"Nodular sclerosis","bool":false}]},{"id":57,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following factors will cause sickling in sickle cell disease?","answers":[{"option":"Dehydration","bool":true},{"option":"Alcohol","bool":false},{"option":"Anti-malarials","bool":false},{"option":"Fava beans","bool":false},{"option":"Alkalosis","bool":false}]},{"id":58,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"What characteristic cells are seen in Hodgkin lymphoma?","answers":[{"option":"Teardrop cells","bool":false},{"option":"Smudge cells","bool":false},{"option":"Target cells","bool":false},{"option":"Reed-Sternberg cells","bool":true},{"option":"Sezary cells","bool":false}]},{"id":59,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"What mutation is the most common cause of acute promyelocytic leukemia?","answers":[{"option":"t(14;18)","bool":false},{"option":"t(15;17)","bool":true},{"option":"t(8;14)","bool":false},{"option":"t(11;18)","bool":false},{"option":"t(9;22)","bool":false}]},{"id":60,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following does NOT predispose an individual to warm autoimmune hemolytic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Alpha-methyldopa","bool":false},{"option":"Systemic lupus erythematosus","bool":false},{"option":"Mycoplasma infection","bool":true},{"option":"Quinidine","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic lymphocytic leukemia","bool":false}]},{"id":61,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"BCR-ABL mutation is seen in which leukemia?","answers":[{"option":"Chronic myelogenous leukemia","bool":true},{"option":"Chronic lymphocytic leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Acute lymphoblastic leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hairy cell leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Acute myelogenous leukemia","bool":false}]},{"id":62,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura can be successfully treated by which of the following methods?","answers":[{"option":"Dialysis which remove auto antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"Catheterization which remove plasma cells","bool":false},{"option":"Intravenous infusion which removes the antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet infusion which removes basal cells","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma exchange which remove auto antibodies","bool":true}]},{"id":63,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"What is the main clinical finding in coagulation factor deficiencies?","answers":[{"option":"Eccyhmoses","bool":false},{"option":"Increased bleeding time","bool":false},{"option":"Hemarthrosis","bool":true},{"option":"Pruritis","bool":false},{"option":"Petechiae","bool":false},{"option":"Slow capillary refill","bool":false}]},{"id":64,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"When does relative polycythemia occur?","answers":[{"option":"Dehydration","bool":true},{"option":"Eryhtropoetin producing malignancy","bool":false},{"option":"Exogenous erythropoetin","bool":false},{"option":"Under the sea","bool":false},{"option":"High altitude","bool":false}]},{"id":65,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Intrinsic coagulation is initiated by what factor?","answers":[{"option":"Hageman factor","bool":true},{"option":"Factor II","bool":false},{"option":"Heparin-like factor","bool":false},{"option":"Factor VII","bool":false},{"option":"Rheumatoid factor","bool":false}]},{"id":66,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which type of cells are most commonly associated with chronic lymphocytic leukemia?","answers":[{"option":"Teardrop cells","bool":false},{"option":"Schistocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Smudge cells","bool":true},{"option":"Burr cells","bool":false},{"option":"Target cells","bool":false}]},{"id":67,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Hemoglobinuria during blood transfusion is due to transfusion of which of the following cells?","answers":[{"option":"Red blood cells","bool":true},{"option":"B-cells","bool":false},{"option":"T-cells","bool":false},{"option":"Platelets","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma","bool":false}]},{"id":68,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Red blood cells in sickle cell disease are of what characteristic shape?","answers":[{"option":"Crescent-shaped","bool":true},{"option":"Rod-shaped","bool":false},{"option":"Helmet-shaped","bool":false},{"option":"Teardrop-shaped","bool":false},{"option":"Egg-shaped","bool":false}]},{"id":69,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following agents directly activates plasminogen?","answers":[{"option":"Tissue plasminogen activator (tPA)","bool":false},{"option":"Warfarin","bool":false},{"option":"Urokinase","bool":true},{"option":"Heparin","bool":false},{"option":"Streptokinase","bool":false}]},{"id":70,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"A 16-year-old boy is brought to the clinic with generalized weakness and easy bruising. His complete blood profile shows pancytopenia. Peripheral film shows giant metamyelocytes with large sausage-shaped nuclei. His bilirubin is  3 mg%. The reticulocyte count is 0.5%. Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Hemolytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Acute leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Megaloblastic anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Malaria","bool":false}]},{"id":71,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following is the most common site for extrapulmonary tuberculosis?","answers":[{"option":"Pericardium","bool":false},{"option":"Gastrointestinal tract","bool":false},{"option":"Bones and joint","bool":false},{"option":"Lymph nodes","bool":true},{"option":"Central nervous system","bool":false}]},{"id":72,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"A 21-year-old male presented to the outpatient department with the complaints of shortness of breath, palor and increasing tiredness. On further evaluation he is found to follow a strict vegetarian diet. His laboratory reports show decreased haemoglobin, normal MCHC and MCV of 105 fL. What is most likely the cause of his symptoms?","answers":[{"option":"Vitamin K deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12 deficiency","bool":true},{"option":"Vitamin B6 deficency","bool":false},{"option":"Folate deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency","bool":false}]},{"id":73,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following statement about von Willebrand disease is true?","answers":[{"option":"Type 2 disease is more common and is qualitative","bool":false},{"option":"Type 1 is more common and is qualitative","bool":false},{"option":"Von Willebrand disease has more episodes of bleeding than haemophilia.","bool":false},{"option":"There is decreased Von Willebrand factor with increased factor VIII levels.","bool":false},{"option":"Factor VIII levels are decreased","bool":true}]},{"id":74,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following statement is true about idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura?","answers":[{"option":"People above the age sixty should undergo screening for diffuse large B cell lymphoma","bool":true},{"option":"A count less than 50,000 is associated with spontaneous bleeding","bool":false},{"option":"There is no need to check for human immunodeficiency virus","bool":false},{"option":"Disease severity cannot be predicted by the degree of thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"This disease is more common in males","bool":false}]},{"id":75,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following statement about polycythemia rubra vera is true?","answers":[{"option":"Headache, dizziness and tinnitus are common complaints.","bool":true},{"option":"It occurs in patients before the age of 40","bool":false},{"option":"It is not associated with peptic ulcer disease.","bool":false},{"option":"Less than 40% of the patients have  JAK-2 V617F mutationn.","bool":false},{"option":"Venesection rarely  gives prompt relief of hyperviscosity symptoms in this disease.","bool":false}]},{"id":76,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"A 27-year-old female presented to the outpatient department with complaints of anemia and also complains of dark-colored urine in the morning. Which of the following is the likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Paroxysmal nocturnal  haemoglobinuria","bool":true},{"option":"G6DP deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Hereditary spherocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic cold haemagglutinin disease","bool":false},{"option":"Polycythaemia","bool":false}]},{"id":77,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"A histopathologist examines a blood film under his microscope which shows small lymphocytes with irregular borders. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Chronic lymphocytic leukaemia","bool":false},{"option":"Acute promyelocytic leukaemia","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic myeloid leukaemia","bool":false},{"option":"Acute lymphoblastic leukaemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hairy cell leukemia","bool":true}]},{"id":78,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following is not a feature of thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura?","answers":[{"option":"thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Central nervous system involvement","bool":false},{"option":"Raised prothrombin time and activated partial thromboplastin time","bool":true},{"option":"Fever","bool":false},{"option":"Renal failure","bool":false}]},{"id":79,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following is true about disseminated intravascular coagulation?","answers":[{"option":"Prothrombin and activated partial thromboplastin time do not aid in diagnosis and prognosis","bool":false},{"option":"It is always associated with an underlying infection","bool":false},{"option":"Tranexamic acid is the mainstray of treatment","bool":false},{"option":"Heparin cannot be given","bool":false},{"option":"It can worsen many conditions such as septicemia etc","bool":true}]},{"id":80,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"A patient's reports show prolonged bleeding time but normal  prothrombin time (PT) and normal activated partial thromboplastin time (APTT). Which defect does the patient most likely have?","answers":[{"option":"Dysfibrinogenaemia","bool":false},{"option":"Deficiency of factors VII,\tX, V,\tprothrombin and fibrinogen","bool":false},{"option":"Deficiency of factors XII, XI, IX, VIII,\t X and V.","bool":false},{"option":"Disorder of platelet function","bool":true},{"option":"Fibrinogen deficiency","bool":false}]},{"id":81,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following statement about paraproteinaemias is true?","answers":[{"option":"It is polyclonal in association with multiple myeloma.","bool":false},{"option":"Paraproteinaemias have no association with rheumatoid arthritis or polymyalgia rheumatica.","bool":false},{"option":"Both  monoclonal and polyclonal immunoglobulins are produced.","bool":false},{"option":"It refers to over-production of one or more classes of immunoglobulin.","bool":true},{"option":"It is monoclonal in association with sarcoidosis.","bool":false}]},{"id":82,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"A male came to the outpatient department with the complaints of epistaxis and mucosal bleeding. Bleeding time is more than 5 minutes. Factor VIII and VIIIC are reduced. There is a history of similar illness in the family. What is your diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Liver failure","bool":false},{"option":"Haemophilia A","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin K deï¬ciency","bool":false},{"option":"Von Willebrand disease","bool":true},{"option":"Christmas disease","bool":false}]},{"id":83,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"A patient came to the outpatient department with the complaints of anemia and lumbar tenderness. His lab reports show Calcium=12 mg/dl, Na=134mmol/L, K=4mmol/L, ESR=100 mm/hr and creatinine=4.8 mg/dl. The doctor suspects multiple myeloma. What should be the initial management?","answers":[{"option":"Non steroidal anti inflammatory drugs","bool":false},{"option":"Cyclophosphamide","bool":false},{"option":"Hydrate the patient","bool":true},{"option":"Blood transfusion","bool":false},{"option":"Steroids","bool":false}]},{"id":84,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following is the most appropriate statement about haematopoietic stem cell transplantation?","answers":[{"option":"Aplastic anemia is a contradiction to stem cell transplantation.","bool":false},{"option":"Haematopoietic stem cell transplantation comes with considerably less morbidity and mortality.","bool":false},{"option":"Infertility is an early complication of stem cell transplantation.","bool":false},{"option":"In allogenic transplantation stem cells are taken from the patient.","bool":false},{"option":"The best results are found in patients with minimal residual disease who are less than 20 years of age who have a HLA-identical sibling donor.","bool":true}]},{"id":85,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"Which of the following statements is incorrect about deep venous thrombosis (DVT) in pregnancy?","answers":[{"option":"Lower molecular weight heparin (LMWH) is given as treatment","bool":false},{"option":"Diagnosed by doppler ultrasound","bool":false},{"option":"Usually unilateral","bool":false},{"option":"Women with a previous history of venous thromboembolism (VTE) who are receiving warfarin or other oral anticoagulants as prophylaxis should have these stopped prior to conception","bool":false},{"option":"Measurement of D-dimer levels is used in diagnosis","bool":true}]},{"id":86,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"An old man was rushed to the emergency department with hemoglobin levels of less than 6 mg/dl. His blood type isnât available. Which blood type can be transfused to him in order to save his life?","answers":[{"option":"Fresh frozen plasma","bool":false},{"option":"O negative","bool":true},{"option":"AB negative","bool":false},{"option":"O positive","bool":false},{"option":"AB positive","bool":false}]},{"id":87,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"A young female patient came to the clinic with primary amenorrhea and knee haemarthrosis. Her brother is a known case of haemophilia. What is the karyotype of this patient?","answers":[{"option":"XXY mosaicism","bool":false},{"option":"XXY","bool":false},{"option":"XO","bool":true},{"option":"XY","bool":false},{"option":"XX","bool":false}]},{"id":88,"info":"3rd-year/hematology/2017","question":"An African patient came to the clinic with a history of multiple blood transfusions in the past. Which disease is he most likely suffering from?","answers":[{"option":"Beta thalassemia Major","bool":true},{"option":"Hereditary elliptocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Beta thalassemia intermedia","bool":false},{"option":"Haemoglobin H disease","bool":false},{"option":"Hydrops fetalis","bool":false}]}]
export default arr